Just over a decade ago, the last native speaker
of Yurok died. And the language – which had been
spoken by indigenous people in California for
more than 10,000 years – died with him. And
Yurok isn’t alone; every year, an estimated
nine languages go extinct. That’s why,
if you look at an official count of the total
number of living languages in the world over time,
you can see that … wait, huh?
How are we gaining languages?
Hi, I’m David, and this is MinuteEarth.
First off, even though some languages are
going extinct, others that have been around
for a long time – like Lakurumau, spoken
by a small group of villagers in Papua New
Guinea – are only just being described by
experts, and so they’re only now getting
added to the official count. You know how
there are species that have been around
for ages – like the shrew-like animal called
a gymnure, which has been shrewing around in
the mountains of the Philippines for hundreds
of thousands of years – but they’re only just
being photographed and documented for
the first time? It’s a lot like that.
But by far the biggest reason for the increase
in living languages is the realization that what
we once thought was one language is actually
a group of similar but distinct languages.
Like, until the early 2000s, most experts
considered Arabic – spoken by more than a
billion people – a single language. But
as linguists learned more about all the
different versions of Arabic, they realized
that some versions were so different that
people speaking them couldn’t even
understand each other. As a result,
what used to be one language is now
officially more than 30 different languages.
Actually, that TOO is a lot like what’s going
on with species on Earth; like, for a long time,
scientists considered giraffes to be
a single species. But recent genetic
research has revealed that there are actually
four separately-evolving groups of giraffes,
prompting a proposal to quadruple the
official number of giraffe species out there.
So the number of known languages currently
spoken on Earth and the number of described
species currently living on Earth are both
officially increasing, but only because we're
getting better – and pickier – about documenting
and categorizing what’s out there, not because
we’re actually gaining diversity. I mean,
sure – new species and new languages ARE still
occasionally evolving, but that’s a really slow
process; as our planet globalizes and homogenizes,
existing species and languages are going
extinct way faster than new ones are evolving.
Soon, it’s likely that we’ll reach peak
language and peak species – that is,
we'll have documented and nit-picked basically
all we can, yet we’ll be losing languages and
species faster than ever – so the official counts
will begin to reflect the reality on the ground.
Which is…depressing. Occasionally, though, we
might be able to raise a language or species from
the dead. We’re still working on figuring out how
to clone dinosaurs, but Yurok – that indigenous
language that died in 2013 – is alive again; it’s
actively being taught in some high schools, and
today, more than 300 kids speak it proficiently.
So despite all the linguistic and biological
diversity we’re losing, perhaps – every once in
a while – life – and language – will find a way.
To understand and play with data, like the number
of languages or species in the world - or anything
else you’re interested in - you need to practice,
and Brilliant is where you learn by doing,
with thousands of interactive lessons
in data analysis, math, programming,
and AI. Brilliant helps you build real skills
through hands-on problem-solving based on lessons
created by MIT and CalTech professors and it
recently launched a ton of new data courses,
all of which use real-world data to train you to
see trends and make better-informed decisions.
I’m currently making my way through their
new course on exploring data visually, where
I’m playing with real data sets from sources like
Starbucks and AirBnB. To try everything Brilliant
has to offer for free for a full 30 days, visit
brilliant.org/MinuteEarth or click on the link
in the description. You’ll also get 20% off an
annual premium subscription. Thanks Brilliant.