it is the worst nightmare of the Secret
Service an attack on the president of
the United States while he's traveling
hidden beneath this manhole cover is a
bomb that went undetected and it can be
triggered
remotely just seconds from now the
presidential motorcade will be passing
over exactly this spot but this is not
the only
danger a few blocks away there is is a
second fret located in a dimly lit room
a sniper is overlooking the intersection
where the president will soon
be and a little further down the road a
van with tinted windows is parked close
to the blocked off streets inside a man
is preparing a rocket launcher that will
soon be aimed at the
motorcade fortunately these free
scenarios are purely fictional but they
will demonstrate the rigorous effort the
Secret Service undertakes to ensure that
the president remains secure during
travel while the president is still
about 2 minutes away from the manhole
cover with the bomb the first car of the
motor Cate the route car is already
driving past this
spot this car together with the pilot
car ensures that the road is clear of
obstructions the sweepers which are
primarily motorcycles follow the route
car and pilot car and help clear the
road
ahead however they are unable to
identify the bomb and the core of the
motorcade consisting of Secret Service
vehicles with the president on board is
approaching as the president's limousine
rolls towards the manhole cover a person
remotely pulls the trigger and
suddenly nothing
happens
the remote trigger didn't work and that
is because of this car the electronic
countermeasure Suburban one of the most
technically impressive vehicles in the
motor Cate on its roof antennas emit
radio frequencies that drown out any
bomb activation signal this technique is
called barage jamming and it essentially
works by the antennas emitting such a
strong noise signal that other signals
simply cannot get through
and so the motorcade continues
undisturbed towards the second threat
the sniper in the
window located behind the electronic
countermeasure Suburban is the
president's vehicle commonly known by
its nickname the Beast however you can
never be sure in which car the president
is as there are two identical
presidential limousines on the road
following behind are two cars carrying
the president's most important security
Personnel ready to take action in the
event of an attack this is the so-called
halfback in which the president's
personal Secret Service agents are
located no matter what happens these
agents will stay with the
president the other car carries the
counter assault team these heavily armed
agents can remain on site and fight off
and attack this creates a secure buffer
between attackers and the
president Behind these cars are the
control car and the support car these
transport additional Secret Service
agents essential presidential staff as
well as the president's personal
doctor but unknown to any of them they
are currently approaching another threat
as the motorcade arrives at the
intersection the sniper has scouted
out the fact that there are two
identical cars makes it difficult for
the shooter but unfortunately he catches
a glimpse through the glass aims and
pulls the
trigger such a scenario naturally brings
back memories of the 1963 assassination
of John F Kennedy who was shot while
driving his motorcade through
Dallas since that time the presidential
limousine has undergone many changes
Kennedy's car was a specially modified
1961 Lincoln
Continental unfortunately though only a
few of the adjustments made were related
to security
improvements the car was retrofitted
with a luxurious heating and air
conditioning system as well as lights
Sirens fire extinguishers and radio
telephones for communication the car was
also extended to include a middle row of
jump pump seats that can fold away when
not in use in addition the roof was made
to be completely removable and the
cushion on the rear Bank where the
president sits was raised both these
modifications were designed to make the
president more visible to the public
unfortunately it also made him more
vulnerable after Kennedy's assassination
the car was massively rebuilt a top of
bulletproof glass was installed and the
body of the car was now protected with
titanium armor perhaps somewhat symbolic
the light convertible appearance
representative of a hopeful time was
built up into a tank set to protect his
more divisive
successor luckily today's limousine is
well prepared for such an attack and the
shot has absolutely no chance of
success
the current Beast has been in service
since September 2018 and is a completely
custombuilt vehicle by General Motors
although visually reminiscent of a sedon
the car was actually built based on a
truck platform this was necessary to
support the over 15,000lb heavy armored
vehicle the interior is hermetically
sealed against any form of chemical
attack the tires are able to continue
driving even when shot and the doors are
8 in thick and equipped with handles
that with the switch of a button can be
electrified in order to prohibit entry
to
Outsiders always inside the car there is
a storage of blood of the same blood
type as the president it is a luxury
tank designed to withstand any possible
threat but the biggest challenge in our
scenario is Yet to Come As just two
blocks away way the van with the rocket
launcher prepares to test the car's
endurance behind the solid core of
vehicles directly protecting the
president are a few larger Vans these
carry the Press pool of reporters that
travel with the
president this car behind is the ID car
it functions as the motor Cates
Communications Hub relaying information
between the different vehicles and
identify in problems early
on behind that is the Hazardous
Materials mitigation unit a vehicle
equipped to respond to biological
chemical and even nuclear
attacks it carries the necessary
equipment and Personnel to treat the
effects of such an attack
effectively this is the so-called Road
Runner recognizable by the antenna above
the roof this car is the mobile
communication Hub of the motorcade
ensuring that the president is fully
operational at all
times the car provides satellite and
internet communications and it feeds a
direct encrypted link to the Pentagon
allowing the president to hold secure
phone and video conversations even when
on
road at the back of the motorcade a
local ambulance will follow just in case
anything happens and signifying the end
of the motorcade are the so-called rear
guards local police cars that make sure
that no other cars drive into the
motorade from the
back at this point the presidential
limousine arrives at the intersection
with the
van quickly a man jumps
out and aims the rocket launcher
directly at the limousine
[Music]
for this case the presidential
limousines and the electronic
countermeasure vehicle are equipped with
smoke grenades as soon as they are
triggered the cars disappear in the
Smoke preventing a clear line of sight
this so-called infrared smoke screen is
composed in such a way that it conceals
the heat signature of objects that means
that even more complex guided missile
would not succeed in tracking the
target meanwhile the Beast fle the
scene the presidential motorcade is a
highly fought for system although the
enormous number of cars may seem a bit
arbitrary at first glance a closer look
reveals that the different Vehicles all
fulfill different tasks and together
function as a White House on Wheels
though it's probably fair to say that
besides Justified security concerns
there's also some element of projecting
power at play
here today the motorcade managed to
successfully avert three different
dangers but the motorcade is only one
part of a huge security apparatus with
another element being Air Force 1 the
call sign for a heavily modified Boeing
747 on which the president
travels this plane was severely tested
when it served as a refuge for George
Bush during the attacks on the country
on September 11 2001 with the president
spending much of that day on
board for my next video I took a look at
this special perspective on September 11
and you can watch that video already
right now on nebula where I upload all
my videos first and not only not only
that nebula is also where you can see
exclusive videos that I made just for
nebula subscribers such as the one I
produced about the bin Laden raid
detailing how this military operation
unfolded because nebula is a
subscription service I can work with
higher budgets for these videos creating
way more ambitious projects and this
support has enabled me to increase my
production quality for my YouTube videos
as well allowing me to do things I could
have only dreamed of 2 years
ago besides me you can find incredible
shows exclusive to nebula from many
other educational creators as we are all
building this streaming site together
with everything included in one
subscription and if you have a friend or
a family member who is interested in
smart highly produced documentaries and
shows then this December we are offering
a very special gift card with which you
can gift someone nebula access for a
lifetime so please make sure to check
out nebula and thank you so much for
watching this
[Music]
video